<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An Historical account of the most remarkable transactions betwixt the Duke of Savoy and the French King contained in several letters pass'd betwixt them before the rupture / translated from the original French copies.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1690</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 65 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A43876</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H2097</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R4787</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11889920</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11889920</idno>
            <idno type="VID">50422</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A43876)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 50422)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 35:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An Historical account of the most remarkable transactions betwixt the Duke of Savoy and the French King contained in several letters pass'd betwixt them before the rupture / translated from the original French copies.</title>
                  <author>Victor Amadeus I, King of Sardinia, 1666-1732.</author>
                  <author>Louis XIV, King of France, 1638-1715.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>34 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Richard Baldwin ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1690.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Harvard University Libraries.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:50422:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:50422:1"/>
            <p>AN Hiſtorical Account OF THE MOST REMARKABLE TRANSACTIONS BETWIXT THE DUKE of <hi>SAVOY</hi> AND THE FRENCH KING: CONTAINED In ſeveral LETTERS paſs'd betwixt Them before the Rupture.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tranſlated from the Original</hi> French <hi>Copies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="license">
                        <p>LICENS'D,</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>J. FRASER.</signed>
                           <date>
                              <hi>October</hi> 3. 1690.</date>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Richard Baldwin,</hi> near the <hi>Oxford Arms</hi> in <hi>Warwick-Lane.</hi> MDCXC.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letters">
            <pb facs="tcp:50422:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:50422:2"/>
            <head>AN HISTORICAL ACCOUNT OF THE Moſt Remarkable Tranſactions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>His Royal Highneſs the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi>'s Letter to the <hi>French King</hi>'s Brother, the Duke of <hi>Orleans.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>MONGST the great and many Troubles, under which I am at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, ſeeing none but You capable of giving ſome eaſe to my afflicted Spirits, I hope you'll give me leave to do what unfortunate men have only left to do; that is to ſay, To ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie their Conduct, and to demonſtrate their reaſons to thoſe that are not yet ſo far from all Equity, as to refuſe to pity them. What have I ever done elſe to the King, than to ſerve him in the moſt ſubſtantial things he deſir'd of me? Have not I ſacrific'd to his ſatisfaction the Valleys of <hi>Lucerne,</hi> to my own preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice, and againſt all the principles of true Politicks?
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:50422:3"/>Did not I conſent to give him three of my Regiments, at the ſame inſtant his Ambaſſador made the firſt men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it? Is it not evident, that to pleaſe the King, I have abandon'd my Intereſt, my Countrey, and my Perſon, by ſuch compliances, that have drawn upon me a great averſion of all the Proteſtant Powers, of the Emperour, of the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> and of all the Confederate Princes? Wherein have I ever diſpleas'd the King?</p>
               <p>His Ambaſſadors have ſometimes made their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints about ſome little inſignificant things, at thouſand of which would not be able to balance the leaſt part of thoſe ſubſtantial Services which I have mention'd, nor the continual marks I have given of a ſtrict adherency to the King's Intereſts. A Gentleman of <hi>Nice</hi> raiſes, without my leave, and without deſiring it, ſome Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers in the ſaid place, againſt ſeveral Declarations of my Predeceſſors, at the ſame time I am there actually preſent: This is not enough, he liſts ſome of thoſe that belong to my Regiment of Guards: I have the goodneſs not to ſuffer him to be try'd at the Seſſions, nor his Goods be ſeized according to Cuſtom; and I content my ſelf to ſend him to Priſon, only to prevent the ill example he had given by his behaviour: And yet, after all, they pretend to make a great buſineſs on't, as if I was oblig'd to ſuffer tamely this Inſolency and Affront of one of my own Subjects in my very preſence, inſtead that they ſhould have taken notice of my moderation.</p>
               <p>I have given the King three Regiments, partly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed out of the principal Nobility of this Countrey; there is a conſiderable number of Gentlemen and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of my Subjects in thoſe Troops; I am willing,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:50422:3"/>for my greater recommendation, to give the King with my own hands ſuch as he may deſire to have above the ſaid number: but I do not intend to give my Subjects full licenſe to act againſt the Law, and to deviate from that Loyalty they naturally owe to their Sovereign. Nevertheleſs, thoſe that do it, are not puniſh'd for it, their Goods are not ſeiz'd, and I do expreſly prohibit not to indict them for ſome impertinent and ſeditious words; neither do I trouble their Parents for it: yet, after all, if I do not applaud their exorbitancy, my paſt Services are forgotten, and I have no good inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions for thoſe of His Majeſty.</p>
               <p>There is a reciprocal agreement made about the reſtoring of the Deſerters of the Gariſon of <hi>Pigneroll, Perouſe,</hi> and <hi>Caſſal,</hi> and of thoſe of my Troops. This is not at all executed on the ſide of the ſaid Gariſons; for if they reſtore One, they retain Fifty: and yet they make a great noiſe, as if the agreement was not obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved on my ſide. Of thoſe Troops which for the King's Service I entertain'd in the Valleys of <hi>Lucerne,</hi> a great many deſerted to <hi>Pignerol:</hi> but the Governour pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, either, That he had no Authority over thoſe Deſerters, becauſe they had liſted themſelves amongſt ſome Recruits which were made for other Regiments; or, That they were to be exchanged with thoſe Troops of his Majeſty that were out of the place; or they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed them ſometimes downright, pretending that there was an <hi>Amneſty</hi> of the King in favour of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerters; as if an <hi>Amneſty</hi> of the King, that only regards thoſe that deſert in his own Kingdom, could be made uſe of by thoſe that deſerted out of my Troops, far from coming back, as it is expreſly requir'd in <hi>Amne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties</hi> of ſuch nature. It has been declar'd at <hi>Caſſal,</hi> That
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:50422:4"/>they would neither render nor re-take any Deſerter: This is a thing I do not complain of; for there ſeems to be a reciprocal Equity in <hi>not asking,</hi> and in <hi>not gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving back:</hi> but then the Gariſon of <hi>Caſſal</hi> has no reaſon to complain neither.</p>
               <p>Give me leave about this Subject to inform you of a thing that has made ſo great a noiſe. Some Officers of <hi>Pignerol</hi> having made their complaints, That ſome of their Deſerters were to be found in the Valleys of <hi>Lucerne,</hi> I gave order, That they ſhould be reſtored; and, withal, leave that they might go themſelves to diſcover them. They took along with them a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geant that had deſerted out of a Regiment belonging to the ſaid Valleys: The Officers of the ſaid Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſeiz'd him as ſoon as they ſaw him: I was told of it in a Letter: I gave them, according to my cuſtom in ſuch matters, a general Anſwer, that is to ſay, To do what they found juſt, having no mind to condemn the Deſerters my ſelf. The Sergeant did himſelf con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs that he had deſerted; he was try'd, and condemn'd according to Law. Should a Deſerter not have been ſeiz'd, that had the impudence to come before his Officers, to encourage (by his ſo fine example) the reſt of the Regiment to deſert as well as He? Does the agreement made to reſtore the Deſerters, mention, not to take them our ſelves when they are to be found in our own Territories, from whence they deſerted, only becauſe ſome Officers had the impudence to take them along with them? Ought we to think that it is the King's pleaſure that we leave off being Sovereigns in Foreign Countreys, when a Criminal is at the ſuit of a <hi>French</hi> Officer, and that there be no Juſtice for them there? Ought we to think that he would have
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:50422:4"/>us take there more care, than in his own Kingdom? And yet this is the very thing that has been ſo much exaggerated, to prove that I have no good intentions for the King's Service.</p>
               <p>They have continu'd ſecretly to raiſe Soldiers in my Territories for the King's Service: They are exhauſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of Men; I cannot find enough to complete my own Regiments. I endeavour to retain my own Subjects by ſome ſlight demonſtrations, without troubling thoſe any more that do not obſerve it, ſetting at liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty thoſe that have been impriſon'd, as ſoon as they deſire it. So great a moderation is not at all taken no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of; as if a Sovereign ought to contribute himſelf to the exhauſting his Countrey of Men, and that he ought to leave off making uſe of his own Subjects, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be employ'd in the King's Service, without ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to take notice of it, without being ask'd or thank'd for it.</p>
               <p>Some years ago, the King deſiring to make ſome Recruits in <hi>Savoy</hi> for his Regiments of <hi>Rouſillon</hi> and St. <hi>Laurent,</hi> did conſent that I might make ſome Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cruits for my ſervice in the Provinces of <hi>Dauphine, Lion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nois,</hi> and <hi>Provence:</hi> And tho' thoſe Recruits are very expenſive, and come to nothing at all, by reaſon of the great number of thoſe that deſert either on the way, or as ſoon as they are arriv'd in this Countrey; yet I never fail'd to give order in <hi>Savoy,</hi> as often as the Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers of the ſaid Regiment arriv'd there with a Letter of Monſieur <hi>de Louvois,</hi> to let them make their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cruits. It has been repreſented ſome few months ago, to two or three Officers that were come for the ſame purpoſe, That <hi>Savoy</hi> was exhauſted of Men; that it had very much ſuffer'd the laſt year, endeavouring to
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:50422:5"/>hinder the Incurſions of thoſe of <hi>Lucerne,</hi> and ſome <hi>French</hi> Proteſtants; and that to continue to contribute to the King's ſatisfaction, there would, according to all appearance, be no leſs difficulty this year to furniſh enough Men to the ſame end; deſiring the ſaid Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers to put off their Recruits till ſome more conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent time. The Count <hi>de Rebenac</hi> having ſpoke ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of it here, the ſame reaſons were made known to him; withal telling him, That it was no refuſal, but only a putting it off for a better time, to make the ſaid Recruits with ſo much the more conveniency; and tho' he ſeem'd to be ſatisfied with theſe juſt reaſons, yet endeavours have been made to draw an ill conſequence out of it, to the prejudice of my good intentions for the King's Service; as if the various troubles of this poor Countrey, which it has been forc'd to undergo, were not evident to all the world, and that is only with a deſign to contribute to his Majeſty's ſatisfaction.</p>
               <p>I have endeavour'd to find ſome legal means to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent the open Cheats which the ordinary Expreſſes of <hi>Lions</hi> commit, to the prejudice of my Cuſtoms. The Poſthouſe of <hi>Turin</hi> has been transferred to a more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient place, that indeed is much nearer to the Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom-houſe; but that has no entring there yet, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out changing any thing that was uſual before: the ſaid Expreſſes refuſe to go to the Cuſtom-houſe; they come in with ſome Waggons laden with Merchandiſe, commit all manner of abuſes without end, and meerly out of ſpight; and yet I have ſuffer'd for ſome conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable time, with an unpreſidented moderation, all theſe Proceedings, that could not be practis'd in the leaſt Town that has ſome right of Liberty.</p>
               <p>You know what has paſs'd concerning the Prince of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:50422:5"/>
                  <hi>Carignan.</hi> Why is it not poſſible that I can altogether forget it? for I do not remember, but with the greateſt affliction in the world, that I have been forc'd to exile out of my Territories the firſt Prince of my Blood; Why, becauſe he did marry.</p>
               <p>I run over and examine all my Actions, and I find no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe that in the leaſt can be taken hold of by thoſe that pleaſe themſelves to cenſure my Actions before the King, than my journey to <hi>Venice,</hi> which the Marqueſs of <hi>Arcy</hi> has ſo often talk'd of before and after it. I confeſs, that I was very glad to have an opportunity to know the Duke of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> and to ſee at the ſame time the ſo much-renown'd City of <hi>Venice.</hi> I proteſt, That I did not think nor reſolve on't, till at a time when I could not make it known to the King, and receive his advice, without loſing the opportunity of executing my deſign. I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you ſeriouſly to conſider of what ill conſequence it could be, and what reaſon the King has to complain of it, ſince I did not do it, when my Father of bleſſed memory went to <hi>Padua</hi> for the ſame reaſon, and that I did not know the King did meddle with Travels that other Princes undertake. Sure it is, that what has fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed, has made it evident, that there was nothing in this Journey but what is good, honeſt, and that no body can diſapprove.</p>
               <p>It ought not to be forgotten, That I have not always been willing to grant what ſome Ambaſſadors reſiding here, have deſired of me for ſome particular perſons; for ſuch things are for the moſt part drawn from them by my own Subjects, ſollicited by ſome petty Secretaries for a particular intereſt. Beſides, that ſome reſervedneſs in this caſe is very neceſſary, if we are not willing to be troubled every day, and at every hour with ſuch-like re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commendations.</p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:50422:6"/>
               <p>This is all I aſſure you, I can remember of things paſs'd; but now I intend to ſpeak to you about things of a freſher date, till to the time that Monſieur <hi>Cattinat</hi> did explain himſelf about ſome limited Orders he did receive from Court, by the coming back of his Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phew.</p>
               <p>I come for this reaſon to the Conceſſions I obtain'd from the Emperor about the Privilege of Crowned Heads, and ſome Feofs of the Empire hereabouts, that are very convenient for me. If this buſineſs had not been manag'd with all poſſible ſecrecy in this Countrey, it would not have had the leaſt ſucceſs, by reaſon of ſome oppoſition it would have met with from ſome Vaſſals of the Empire; and if ſeveral Princes had had ſome notice of my treating about the ſaid Privilege, it would have been ſpoil'd at its very beginning. This buſineſs does not concern the King, either directly or indirectly, and yet I was reſolv'd to make it known to him before any body elſe; and I had certainly done it, if I had not been pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented by him. You ſay, It is Money that goes to the King's Enemies: It has been deſign'd for the War againſt the <hi>Turks;</hi> and it is ſo very inconſiderable, conſidering the Perſons it went to, that the King wrongs his Greatneſs and Power to take notice on't. The King may eaſily en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage me to do the ſame thing for Him, by ſome conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable effects of his favour; and, in fine, he is too juſt to deſire to deprive a Sovereign Prince, that has the honour to be ſo near related to him, of that Right of Nature, of Buying, Selling, and making Bargains, and regulate to his liking thoſe things that do not in the leaſt concern him. There are ſo many others that treat with the Emperour, and which the King does not find fault with, that it was the leaſt thing I could expect, after all the marks I have given him of my zeal, and that he would be rather pleas'd
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:50422:6"/>to ſee that I-had not loſt an opportunity which, perhaps, might not have been recovered all my life-time, to obtain the honour of Crowned Heads, and to open my ſelf away to the poſſeſſion of the Imperial Feofs hereabouts, ſeeing that it was for the King's Intereſts, that they ſhould be rather in my hands than in any bodies elſe.</p>
               <p>You'll object, without doubt, That the King having made known to me by his Ambaſſadors his diſliking of this Affair, I ſhould accordingly have left it. I was mightily diſpleaſed it was then no more left in my pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, having already got the Emperour's Proviſionals, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch that my Honour was engag'd, by having given my Word; which a Prince, and every honeſt man, ought to value more than his Life; after which, I made no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flection of part of the Money that was already paid, the reſt of it being paid a little after by Bills of Exchange. The only reaſon why Crowns were ſo much look'd for in this City, and that ſome were coyn'd in my Mint, was, to pay the Merchant with ſome advantage, that had ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanc'd the ſaid Bills. Speak, Sir, how was it poſſible, and how could the King, without violating his natural Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and that admirable Judgment which appears in all his Actions, oblige me to break my Word? And I am ſtill inclin'd to believe, that, after ſecond thoughts, he'll approve my being careful of acquiring two things that do not concern Him in the leaſt, and that are very ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantageous to me.</p>
               <p>Give me leave alſo to anſwer ſome other Complaints which the Ambaſſadour of his Majeſty, and Monſieur <hi>Catinat,</hi> have mingled in their Diſcourſe, and which partly you your ſelf have made to the Marquis of <hi>Dog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liani,</hi> my Ambaſſadour, to wit, that I was treating with His Imperial Majeſty, with the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> with <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:50422:7"/>and <hi>Holland.</hi> To convince his Majeſty that this was a falſe Suppoſition, I have writ you ſeveral times that it was not true: If you do but know me well, you'll eaſily be convinc'd, that this is more than a ſufficient proof; for I had rather loſe all, than tell you a lie. In the mean time I informed the Pope by my Reſident, I have writ to him, and his Nuntio that had ſhew'd the Letter to Monſieur <hi>Cattinat,</hi> that it was not true, and that there had nothing paſs'd, neither was there any thing on foot againſt his Majeſty's Intereſt: that on the contrary, I had done ſeveral things againſt common Civility, and directy againſt my own Intereſt, out of fear of diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing him; having had no Miniſters at the Emperor's, and the Catholick King's Court, to behave my ſelf in this point according to the Marqueſs of <hi>Arcy</hi>'s direction, who could not ſuffer ſo much, as ſome Gentlemen of my Subjects going into <hi>Hungary</hi> to improve themſelves in the Art of War. As for <hi>England,</hi> the ſame reaſon has hindred me that I have ſent no anſwer to an obliging Letter from thence: and concerning the States-General, they have writ to me a Letter, not long ago, in favour of the <hi>Vaudois;</hi> I deſired to be excuſed of doing what they deſired, and that is the only Correſpondence I have had with them.</p>
               <p>There has been ſomething mention'd of Intelligence I kept with certain men in <hi>Dauphine;</hi> this is an Inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the ſame ſtamp with the reſt, but with this diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, that I have reaſon to hope, that by the falſity of this Lye it will be judged, that the reſt is of no better ſoundation. In fine, I am willing to ſubmit my ſelf to the Judgment of His Holineſs, or the Commonwealth of <hi>Venice,</hi> or ſome other Power that I have not juſt rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to ſuſpect; but the King himſelf, by making ſome
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:50422:7"/>juſt Reflexions according to his great Underſtanding, may eaſily ſee the falſity of all theſe Accuſations. And to be plain with you; After the hard uſage I juſt now receive, it ought to be leſs ſtrange, that thoſe who have ſurprized His Majeſty's Equity, as to perſwade him to ſuch extreams with me, have endeavour'd to give ſome few, tho falſe colours, to their Pretences.</p>
               <p>I beſeech you, Sir, to make a parallel of what ſubſtantial things I have actually done for the King's Service, with the ſaid Pretences, and to judge if thoſe ſolid marks I have given of my zeal for the King's Intereſt, do not altogether deſtroy them; and if it be not againſt common ſenſe, to put them into a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel? Throw your eyes upon what follows. Monſieur <hi>de Rebenac,</hi> the King's Ambaſſador, arrives in this Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey; he takes pains to aſſure me of the King's goodneſs in regard to my Perſon: I anſwer it with thoſe earneſt proteſtations ſo often repeated by Me and my Miniſters, of my great acknowledgment and zeal for the King's Service, that ought fully to perſwade him of it. He deſires me to drive the reſt of my Subjects out of the Val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leys; I do conſent to it; he does nothing but entertain me about that buſineſs, and the King's favourable Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion he has of me. Monſieur <hi>Cattinat</hi> arrives at <hi>Pignerol,</hi> he comes to ſee me in this City; the Projects againſt the <hi>Vaudois</hi> ſeems to be his only deſign; he ſpeaks to me a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout it as the only cauſe of his coming. I do eaſily believe it, I let him ſee a Liſt of all my Troops, and that they are not enough to furniſh Gariſons for my Fortreſſes, and to ſend them to ſuch Places where my Service requires their preſence; and nevertheleſs I reſolve to furniſh him with a conſiderable Detachment: He ſeems to be ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied; he deſires to have at <hi>Pignerol</hi> a Conference with
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:50422:8"/>my Officers; I ſend them to him: All his thoughts ſeem to be employed about this Deſign; he makes all ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing preparations for it; he ſays that his Commiſſion regards more thoſe parts that are of this, than the other ſide of <hi>Pignerol;</hi> that it was neceſſary to make all haſte to make an end of the buſineſs with the <hi>Vaudois,</hi> and he ſeems to concern himſelf with nothing elſe. In the mean time there happen'd an Inſurrection in <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dovi;</hi> to appeaſe that, I ſent thither ſome of my Troops, and ſome few of thoſe that are at <hi>Lucerne.</hi> Monſieur <hi>Catinat</hi> lets me know, that ſeeing I was engaged about the Buſineſs of <hi>Mondovi,</hi> if I could not aſſiſt him with the ſame number of Troops I had promis'd, I ſhould let him have at leaſt a part of it. I gave Orders to ſend him a Detachment of 400 Men; he ſeems to be ſatisfied. It Snows very much in the Vallies, ſo there is no Action there. Some few days after, having made an end of the buſineſs of <hi>Mondovi,</hi> and coming back to <hi>Turin,</hi> I un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, that the Kings Troops which we thought were deſign'd for <hi>Burgundy, Catalogne,</hi> and againſt the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants in the Vallies, did advance towards the Borders of my Territories. This Report is confirm'd by the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of His Majeſties Principal Officers, who make it publick, that they intended to put the Dutchy of my Land under Contribution, and accordingly they di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpers'd there ſome Papers that intimated the ſame. No body ſpeaks to me about the Paſſage; I judg that the King has a mind either to take it by force, or that he deſires I ſhould offer it. I do it with all the Security of going and coming back, and all the conveniency of Proviſions in my Territories, with all poſſible Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtations of my Zeal to ſerve him. But this ſignifies no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, Monſieur <hi>Catinat</hi> deſires ſome Commiſſaries
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:50422:8"/>to explain himſelf about the King's Intentions. I ſend him two Perſons to <hi>Pignerol.</hi> He tells them in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Terms, That the King is not ſatisfied with my Behaviour; that he had received Orders to enter his Troops into my Territories, that he would give them Bread, but that I was to furniſh them with Forage, and with a pound of Fleſh each Soldier; and gives a hint that he would write to me ſomething more particular. Thoſe Villages through which he enters into my Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritories, give him what he deſires; after he is enter'd there, he deſires of me in a Letter, to ſend him ſome Body, to whom he might explain himſelf: I ſent to him the Marquiſs of <hi>Ferrero,</hi> whom you formerly knew as my Ambaſſadour. Monſieur <hi>Catinat</hi> begins with Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Complaints; and ends with telling him, that the King expects I ſhould ſend into <hi>France</hi> over the Bridge of <hi>Beauvoiſin</hi> 2000 Foot, and two Regiments of Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goons of my Troops, and that I was to reſolve upon't in 48 hours, in caſe I had no other Propoſals to make. The Marquiſs <hi>Ferrero</hi> did all he could, to let him ſee a ſecond time the little Grounds of his Complaints, the great oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion I had for my own Troops, and in fine, offers him a League defenſive. But Monſieur <hi>Catinat</hi> perſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in his demands, he aſſures him, That I would ſend thoſe Troops over the Bridge <hi>Beauvoiſin</hi> into His Majeſties Service. Monſieur <hi>Catinat</hi> ſeems to be very glad of it, and told the Marquiſs of <hi>Ferrero,</hi> That henceforth we ſhould look upon His Majeſty's Troops as our Friends, and in aſſurance of it, Countermands the March to <hi>Grugliaſch</hi> near <hi>Turin,</hi> becauſe the ſaid Marqueſs had made ſome mention about it. I writ to the Count <hi>Provane,</hi> whom I thought to be at <hi>Paris,</hi> to Repreſent to the King, what the Marqueſs <hi>Ferrero</hi>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:50422:9"/>had told Monſieur <hi>Catinat</hi> without any Succeſs, and to add ſome Propoſals to ſatisfy the King about the Troops, with the Advantage of His Majeſties Service, and the leaſt Prejudice of my own. What will you ſay, when you hear, that neither Monſieur <hi>Catinat</hi>'s, nor my Expreſs could not at all return; that he leaves briskly <hi>Veillane,</hi> and comes to <hi>Orbaſſan,</hi> from whence he ſends a Commiſſary to let me know, that the Troops were not enough to ſatisfy the King, that he deſires ſome other aſſurance of my good Intentions for the King's Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice; that he did not poſitively know what it was, but believ'd it might regard ſome place. That Monſieur <hi>Catinat</hi> expects an Anſwer in Twenty four hours; that it was about Eight or Nine, that about the ſame time to morrow he did expect ſome Propoſals, for want of which he would begin to commit Hoſtilities. I ſend him the Abbot of <hi>Verrue;</hi> Monſieur <hi>Catinat</hi> repeats his Complaints, and deſires ſome Aſſurance of my good In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions. He is deſired to tell, if he had any Power from the King to Treat. He anſwers, That he has none, but that he may accept ſome places in the King's Name. We deſire to know what Place he expects; he makes ſome difficulty to tell it, and deſires we ſhould gueſs it; at laſt he ſays, That the Communication of <hi>Pignerol,</hi> and the Cittadel of <hi>Caſſal</hi> muſt be aſſured; but ſays at the ſame time, they made no Reflection upon the new City of <hi>Aſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Popes <hi>Nuntio</hi> goes to him, in order to accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>date Matters betwixt us; he ſhows him my Letter, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I aſſure him, That I was no ways a treating againſt the King, no, not ſo much as in my Thoughts; but all this without effect. The Marqueſs <hi>Ferrero,</hi> and the Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bot
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:50422:9"/>of <hi>Verrue</hi> return thither, they hear nothing but the ſame things repeated. The Marquiſs <hi>Ferrero</hi> returns thither once more alone, with a Letter from the Marquiſs <hi>de</hi> S. <hi>Thomas,</hi> wherein he ſhows my readineſs to ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the King, with an aſſurance of my good intentions. He is extreamly ſurprized to hear out of Mounſieur <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinat</hi>'s own mouth, that he had not ſpoken of an aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance in the ſingular, but in the plural number; that he had given it ſufficiently to underſtand to the Abbot of <hi>Verrue,</hi> yet it ſeem'd to be the ſame thing to that Abbot, and to the Commiſſary, to ſpeak in the Plural, inſtead of the Singular Number, as they have done both. But Mounſieur <hi>Catinat,</hi> who aim'd at his ends, perſiſted in this Opinion, and declared afterwards, that there was nothing but the Cittadel of <hi>Turin</hi> and <hi>Verrue</hi> that could ſatisfie the King; that in caſe they were not put in 24 Hours into his hands, he could not longer defer to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit Hoſtilities; as if the entring with an Army into a Country, and to make them ſubſiſt at the expences of the People, were great marks of Friendſhip: And yet he would by no means, nay he had no Power to treat about the conditions, which is in plain <hi>Engliſh</hi> to live at diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>In this great extremity, ſeeing my People at the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of a Foreign Army, I thought fit to give my ſelf the Honour to ſend to the King a Letter, the Copy of which I have join'd to this, and ſent it to Mounſieur <hi>Catinat</hi> by the Count of <hi>Marcenaeſe.</hi> He agreed to ſuſpend all actions of Hoſtilities, and diſpatch'd immediately his Nephew to carry the Letter to the King with all poſſible ſpeed. And indeed, his ſpeed was ſo great, that he was but few Hours above a ſeven-night a going and coming. Mounſieur <hi>Catinat</hi> gave me notice of his Arrival by ſend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:50422:10"/>me His Majeſties Anſwer, the Copy of which I have alſo join'd to this. I confeſs I was mightily troub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to ſee a Letter writ with ſo much reſervedneſs, and that did not give me the leaſt ſign of the King's reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to me, which I did expect; and far from giving me the leaſt hopes about the reſtoring of my Places, he gives me ſufficiently to underſtand, that he required long proofs of my Affection before he could be perſuaded of it; inſomuch, that if theſe things altogether falſe and ſuppoſititious, and ſome other ſlight ones, could ſo eaſily perſwade him to the depriving me of the ſaid Places, would he ever want ſome pretences to retain them? I ſent nevertheleſs the Marqueſs <hi>Ferrero</hi> and the Marqueſs of S. <hi>Thomas</hi> to Monſieur <hi>Catinat</hi> with a full Power to Treat. They endeavoured to acquaint themſelves with his Power and his Sentiments: The firſt was in very good form, but the other anſwered little my expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>For beginning with the Troops, inſtead that he had always ſaid they were to go into <hi>France,</hi> by way of the Bridg of <hi>Beauvoiſin,</hi> he inſiſts that they were to join his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my that was to act againſt the Dutchy of <hi>Milan,</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently engage my ſelf into an offenſive War, without knowing why, or who in the ſame manner as Tributa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries are oblig'd to March, putting my Territories to the diſcretion of Friends as well as Enemies, and making it the Seat of War, and in caſe it ſhould have been the King's intereſt to recal his Troops out of <hi>Italy,</hi> I ſhould have been left to the Mercy of a Powerful Enemy, whom I had drawn upon me, without having the leaſt reaſon to complain of it; to all which Mounſieur <hi>Cati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nat</hi> did only Anſwer, That he would promiſe the King ſhould never call back his Troops, before I was ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:50422:10"/>ſecured of my Enemies. You may judge if ſo ſlight a promiſe was ſecurity enough to a Prince, who ſhould have offended all his Neighbours, only to pleaſe a King that deſires my Troops, my beſt places, and to make my Territories the ſeat of War, pretending theſe were the only means left to keep me in his Favour. In fine, all what theſe Miniſters repreſented to him about it, ſignified nothing at all, and Monſieur <hi>Catinat</hi> ſtrongly perſiſted to have my Troops, not to ſend them into <hi>France,</hi> as he had always ſaid, but to act againſt the Dutchy of <hi>Milan.</hi> When they were about the point of the Cittadel, it was always hoped that the King would have given order to Monſieur <hi>Cattinat,</hi> to accept ſome equivalent, as I had deſired of His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, but without ſucceſs. It was repreſented, that I would be expoſed in that Town to the capriciouſneſs of a Governor, and to ſome other accidents that hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen but too often between the Citizens and a Foreign Gariſon; that they muſt have found ſome expedient to ſecure me againſt it. Monſieur <hi>Catinat</hi> did, indeed, propoſe, that the little Gate, towards the Town, ſhould only be opened, and that the Soldiers ſhould be kept in a very ſtrict Diſcipline. Judge, I beſeech you Sir, of the delicacy of theſe expedients. At laſt he ſays, that this was not foreſeen; that they would make an Inventory of what they found in the Cittadel, and that it ſhould be reſtored by a Peace. Do not be angry, that I tell you, that the little ſucceſs my great ſubmiſſion to the King met with, and the great perſiſtance of deſiring the Cit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tadel, without making choice of ſome other place in <hi>Piedmont,</hi> did augment my troubles, ſeeing I muſt ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther leave my Capital City, or live there without either dignity or ſecurity. I ſent again my Chancellor, and the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:50422:11"/>Marquiſs <hi>Mouroux,</hi> to Monſieur <hi>Catinat,</hi> to make a new tryal about my Troops, and to ſee if there was ſome hopes left to find ſome expedient about the Cittadel; but they found neither one nor the other. I ſend my Chancellor again to him the ſame day, to make ſome new endeavour. He propoſed to Monſieur <hi>Catinat</hi> ſome plauſible means, which he rejected; It was, that I would put the Cittadel into the Pope's, or the <hi>Switzer</hi>'s hands; That the Governor ſhould be to the King's liking; That the Gariſon ſhould be pay'd by His Majeſty; and that the Governor ſhould promiſe, that in caſe I ſhould really do any thing againſt the King's intereſt, he would put the Cittadel into his hands. The ſame Expedient was very near made uſe of by the late King your Father, being in this Country in perſon, much more might His Majeſty have been ſatisfied with it, having <hi>Pignerol, Caſſal, Verrue,</hi> and ſome of my Troops in his poſſeſſion. In fine, the refuſing of ſo generous propoſals, has made the Idea of my misfortunes ſo much the more terrible, having nothing for my ſecurity; but finding that at the ſame manner as Monſieur <hi>Catinat</hi> having fix'd my Troops, and ſeem'd to be pleaſed about my conſenting to it, yet did nevertheleſs make ſome new demands, ſo far above the former, as alſo the deſiring firſt of my Troops going into <hi>France,</hi> by way of the Bridge of <hi>Beauvoiſin,</hi> and then the inſiſting on the joining of them with his Army; ſo after being in poſſeſſion of the Cit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tadel and <hi>Verrue,</hi> he may make ſome more extravagant demands: For, in fine, to be plain, after one thing is done without reaſon, we muſt expect to do a great ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more.</p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:50422:11"/>
               <p>I have not been able to put out of my troubled Mind ſome Reflections I made about the King's breaking a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſive League made for his Service, and at his Deſire, without any Formality, and without ſaying the leaſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liging word. He has broken it by two Lines in his Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, in which he tells his Ambaſſadour, That after the Month was paſs'd he would pay no more the 100000 Crowns according to our Treaty.</p>
               <p>I could never obtain the ſending back of my three Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giments I have ſent to ſerve his Majeſty, though it was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly ſaid, That he would ſend them back as ſoon as I had occaſion for them. The neceſſity of which has been evident enough. He has obliged me to raiſe ſome Troops which I ſtood in no necceſſity of. How could I be aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured that the Treaty, and Monſieur <hi>Catinat</hi>'s Promiſes, would have been more ſolid, and ſtricter obſerved, when two Places of ſo great importance as the Cittadel of <hi>Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rin</hi> and <hi>Verrue</hi> are, ſhould have been reſtored? If there be any difference, it is this, that it would have been eaſier to continue a League Defenſive, to ſend back the three Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giments according to the agreement, than to render the above-mentioned Places: Theſe words, to <hi>give</hi> and to <hi>render,</hi> are very hard to be executed; and he that is forced to <hi>give,</hi> has great reaſon to avoid it as much as he can, and he that reſolves upon't, ought to prepare him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf for patience; for he that finds himſelf obliged to <hi>ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> has no leſs pains to perſwade himſelf to it. Monſieur <hi>Catinat</hi> did pretend, that the Letter I writ to the King was an Engagement. I beſeech you to judg of it by what you'l find in the Margin of a Copy of the ſaid Letter which I ſend you.</p>
               <p>In ſine, Sir, after all the ill uſage I received from the King, I am ſure, if he would give himſelf the trouble to hear the reading of this Letter, he would not deſire to be Judg of this Affair; and if he did deſire it, I ſeriouſly
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:50422:12"/>believe he could not hinder himſelf from pronouncing in my favour.</p>
               <p>My Chancellor has writ a Letter to Monſieur <hi>Catinat,</hi> of which I ſend you a Copy, as alſo another of his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer. After which having demanded Contributions in my Territories, and I hearing of nothing but Threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, was forced to accept the Succours, which thoſe that always look'd upon me as a French-man, had the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neroſity to offer me in this great Extremity to which I am reduced; which I did not conſent to, till after I had left no Stone unturned to keep me from that neceſſity. This is ſo very great, that I do not think to flatter my ſelf ſo much, as to believe that all <hi>Europe</hi> will pitty me, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out excepting the moſt generous and juſt Men in <hi>France.</hi> Good God! how was it poſſible it ſhould be for the King's Intereſt to oppreſs a Prince, who has the honour to be ſo near related him, who has given him ſuch Subſtantial marks of his Zeal and Affection, whoſe Countries are ſurrounded by thoſe of his Majeſty's, and who by the reſt of the World is taken to be a French-man? What will thoſe Princes ſay, which <hi>France</hi> would fain ſeparate from the contrary party? Is it not as much as to let them know, that they have no Hopes, and to fear all, conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the uſage I receive? Is the World not enough in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed of the vaſt Deſigns of <hi>France,</hi> without diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering them ſo much in deſiring to drive me out of the Cittadel of my ordinary Reſidence, and another very conſiderable Place? Will the Princes of <hi>Italy</hi> believe that it is in order to defend them from their Enemies, of which they have none? or, to open the way to ſome greater Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts, making the beginning by him, who far from fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any Enterpriſes from him had all reaſon in the World to relie on his Protection? Pardon, Sir, the prolixity of this Letter, and do not aſcribe it to any thing but to juſtify to you my Behaviour, after having made uſe of all hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:50422:12"/>Prudence could furniſh me with. I hope that God Almighty will not abandon the Juſtice of my Cauſe, that he'll fortify my weakneſs; and that the conſolation of a Prince, whom they endeavour to drive out of a part of that he has inherited from his Anceſtors, will be the darling Work of Divine Providence. Pity me in my Misfortunes, but aſſure your ſelf, that having no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to reproach me with, I look upon it with Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage; and in caſe I ſhould happen to be a Prince with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Country (which by God's Aſſiſtance I hope I ſhall not) I'le nevertheleſs maintain thoſe Sentiments, and that greatneſs of Soul, which is anſwerable to my Birth, and worthy of a Son, that intends to honour you as a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther all his Life-time, and that ever will be entirely yours.</p>
               <p>Since the writing of this Letter, I have received one from Monſieur <hi>Catinat,</hi> which I ſend you a Copy of, as as alſo of the Anſwer I ſent him, and how he did reply to it. Methinks that after what has paſs'd, I am not in the wrong to deſire to treat in Writing, and that all the World will eaſily agree, that it is a mark of the uprightneſs of my Proceedings, and the ſincerity of my Intentions, aſſuring you again, that what Monſieur <hi>Catinat</hi> mentions about a precedent Engagement, is nothing but a meer Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, and that I have had none, either with the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror or the Catholick King till the third of this Month, when Monſieur <hi>Catinat</hi> cut off all manner of Treaties, and intimated Contributions to ſeveral of my Territo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>This Letter was not ſent till</hi> June <hi>the</hi> 24th, 1690.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:50422:13"/>
               <head>His Royal Highneſſ's Letter to the French King, <hi>May</hi> the <hi>20th, 1690.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Monſieigneur,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Am infinitely troubled to ſee that thoſe falſe Colours which I have been blacken'd with in the Eyes of your Majeſty, have had ſo much power over your Mind, as to deprive me of the honour of your Favour, which I have always valued more than my life. I have nothing left in this extremity as conſolation of being able to juſtify my ſelf before your Majeſty, but that I have not drawn this Misfortune upon me by the leaſt want of Zeal for your Royal Service, of which I'le make a Glory to continue to give ſome real Marks on all Occaſions. When Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur <hi>Catinat</hi> let me know, you deſired part of my Troops, of which I have not very many; I did aſſure him that your Majeſty was Maſter of them, and that they were to paſs the Mountains immediately to go to ſerve your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty. He has given me ſince to underſtand, that your Will and Pleaſure was, to have ſome places in <hi>Piedmont</hi> in aſſurance of my good Intentions; and although your Majeſty ſtands in no need of any other Aſſurance, than that of my Heart, which is entirely yours, yet having deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Monſieur <hi>Catinat</hi> to ſpeak ſomewhat plainer, and he having at laſt told me that the Cittadel of <hi>Turin</hi> and <hi>Verrue</hi> were aim'd at, I am ready to give your Majeſty ſo ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantial a proof of my ſubmiſſion, as the delivery of thoſe two places into your hands will be, humbly intreating you, that you would be pleaſed to do it upon ſuch Terms, as a Prince that has the honour to be ſo near related to you, may reaſonably expect from the Goodneſs and Genero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of ſo great a King; but if your Majeſty would be pleaſed to make choice of ſome other place in <hi>Piedmont</hi>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:50422:13"/>inſtead of the Cittadel of <hi>Turin,</hi> that I might continue to live there with the dignity of a Sovereign, your Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty would infinitely oblige me. I humbly implore your Majeſty's Generoſity for it, as alſo that you would be pleaſed to hear the Count <hi>Provane</hi> my Ambaſſador, who will ſufficiently ſatisfy your Majeſty about the ill-ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Suſpicions your Majeſty has been inſpired with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning my Behaviour, and who will renew to your Majeſty all the ſincere Proteſtations of my Zeal and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, aſſuring you, that I intend to be all my Life<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>A plain Interpretation of the true Meaning of his Royal Highneſs's Letter to the French King, againſt Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur <hi>Catinat</hi>'s Opinion; who pretends that it is a downright Engagement to deliver up to him the Citta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>del of <hi>Turin</hi> and <hi>Verrue.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>WE do not intend in order to exclude his Pretenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, to waſte much time in conſideration, that all was done by a greater Force, not to ſay by a manifeſt Violence, and with threats of Acts of Hoſtility, againſt a ſurpriz'd and diſarm'd Prince, in caſe he did not ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>render the Cittadel of the very place of his Reſidence, and another of his beſt Places, in 24 Hours, though no Body be able to make the leaſt reply againſt this Reaſon, and that no Body waves to neglect the Obligation of an Engagement, if it be drawn from him by Force. His Royal Highneſs finds that Monſieur <hi>Catinat</hi> puts him to ſuch Extreams, that he deſires the ſaid Cittadel and <hi>Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rue,</hi> without having any power to treat about it, and without being willing to give him time to ſend, with all
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:50422:14"/>poſſible ſpeed, an Expreſs to the King, nor ſuſpend the Acts of Hoſtility.</p>
               <p>His Royal Highneſs has no other Means to put off for a while the Ruin of <hi>Piedmont,</hi> than to write ſo ſubmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive a Letter to the King, that Monſieur <hi>Catinat</hi> reſts ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied with it, and ſends it to his Majeſty by his Nephew, who did but a Week ſtay upon the Way. No Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence can be drawn from this, that may put a ſtrict Obligation upon his Royal Highneſs, as he was willing to believe.</p>
               <p>But let us leave the Reaſons that forced his Royal Highneſs to write the Letter in ſo ambiguous a manner as could have the Effect he ſo much ſtood in need of; and let us come to the true meaning of the ſaid Letter. No Body can deny, that thoſe Clauſes that in ſome reſpect de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend on one another, and that in general make the ſenſe of the Letter, ought not to be ſeparated from it; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can it be denied, that ſome Terms of Reſpect and Submiſſion, one of a leſſer Quality makes uſe of towards one of a Greater, be obligatory in a litteral ſenſe; and when one writes to a great Perſon, that All one has is at his Service, that he may abſolutely diſpoſe of it, it be on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a very obliging Expreſſion, that ſignifies nothing, and conſequently lays no poſitive Obligation on him that made the Complement. When a Soveraign has a mind to ſome rich Hangings, Jewels, a Houſe, a Park, or a Caſtle, belonging to his Subjects, theſe will certainly an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, that every Thing belonging to them is at his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, thinking themſelves happy to have ſomething in their poſſeſſion that does pleaſe him. But do you think, that upon theſe very words the Soveraign may challenge it as a Gift? And a Letter of the ſame nature, is it enough to give a Soveraign a good Title to it, without an evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Oppreſſion? And if it be ſo in regard of a Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign towards his Subjects, much more ought it to be
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:50422:14"/>obſerved by a King towards a Prince, who is infinitely below him; but who in the mean time is a free Prince and Soveraign in his Territories.</p>
               <p>Now if to ſuch Expreſſions be added, the word of Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titioning to Conſent, or to be pleaſed to reflect, or ſome ſuch other Terms, this Addition deſtroys entirely the Force of this preceding Expreſſion, this term Petitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner having no ſignification of it ſelf, if it has no relation to what has been ſaid before. But let us come to our Letter again. The beginning of it, till to Monſieur <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinat</hi>'s Name, is only a repreſentation of the Wrong which has been done to his Royal Highneſs, in making him as black as Hell to the King: he aſſures that he is able to juſtify himſelf, which ſhows his Oppreſſion to be ſo much the greater, becauſe it has been done without Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; and the want of that Reaſon ought to diſpoſe him that has been miſled, of giving over thoſe Pretences that were the Effect of it?</p>
               <p>The following Paragraph, that ſpeaks about the Troops, is poſitive, and ſhows clearly, that his Royal Highneſs has aſſured the King, that the King is Maſter of thoſe Troops Monſieur <hi>Catinat</hi> has deſired of him, and that were immediately to paſs the Mountains to go to his Majeſty's Service. But let us conſider if his Royal Highneſs explains himſelf in the ſame manner about the Places, though it be with all reſpect, and in the moſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liging manner in the World. It is firſt ſaid, That his Majeſty ſtands in no need of ſuch an Aſſurance as he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires: then his Royal Highneſs does not ſay that he gives, but that he is ready to give this ſo ſubſtantial Proof of his ſubmiſſion in delivering up the ſaid Places. Here is the pretended ground of the French Interpretation, they ſuppoſe that his Majeſty gives the ſaid Places, that he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gages himſelf preciſely to ſurrender them; but there is a great difference between giving and being ready to
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:50422:15"/>give; and this term that is ſuppoſed by them to be poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, ſignifies nothing, if you add to it the condition which is undoubtedly implied by the word Intreating, that ſignifies nothing all alone, and is grounded upon the remiſſion of the Places by a conditional Term, inſomuch that the ſuppoſed offering to give, is nothing at all, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the Condition that is ſet to it be fully cleared; and no Body denies that it is an Offering with a Condition, that affirms nothing in it ſelf, without this Condition fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing be made clear by a neceſſary Conſequence.</p>
               <p>Therefore there are required ſome Conditions, in the Plural Number, as the Letter mentions it: But what will theſe Conditions be? They cannot be Arbitrary to the King; they would be no Conditions if they ſhould abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely depend on him. It muſt be ſuch Conditions which the other Party, I mean his Royal Highneſs, agrees to; and this ſo much the more, becauſe the Buſineſs is not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout a mutual Contract, nor a thing which both Parties are equally concerned in, but to deprive a Prince of two moſt principal Parts of his Crown, without either Right or Reaſon, but a meer deſire only which the more Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful has to get the Goods of him that is more Feeble, and who has ſo much the more reaſon not to deprive him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf of it, whatever Complements he has made to the more Powerful; and if at laſt he does conſent to it, the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions ought without doubt to be to his liking.</p>
               <p>And in caſe we had a mind to ſtick to the literal Senſe of the Letter; it is not ſaid the King may make ſuch Conditions as he pleaſes, but ſuch as a Prince, that has the Honour to be ſo near related to him, ought to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect from his Goodneſs and Generoſity. Now, what ought ſuch a Prince to expect from the Goodneſs and Generoſity of ſuch a King, but that he ſhould reſt ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied with his Submiſſions, without being willing to force him to give him his own? Had he not reaſon to believe,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:50422:15"/>that if it came to the worſt, the King would chuſe ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Place inſtead of the Cittadel: And what Condition could his Royal Highneſs propoſe to himſelf in his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, that might not have been far below of what he might have expected from the King's Goodneſs and Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neroſity? According to the literal Senſe of the Letter, the King's Goodneſs and Generoſity is plainly ſuppoſed; and how will you be able to make Violence and Oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion agree with Goodneſs and Generoſity in the ſame Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, after the reſerving of ſuch-like Conditions? The Petition that follows being directed to a great King, are the true Conditions which ought to be hoped for, and which his Royal Highneſs has always expected. And in effect it was not eaſily underſtood, why Monſieur <hi>Catinat</hi> had no Orders from the King about it; which made his Royal Highneſs juſtly fear, that there was ſomething more in the Matter, that was not at all deſigned for his Good.</p>
               <p>In fine, his Royal Highneſs entreats the King to hear the Count of <hi>Provane,</hi> who had full Inſtructions and Power to treat about this Buſineſs: The King has not thought it worth his while to hear him, and Monſieur <hi>Catinat</hi> propoſes nothing that gives the leaſt ſecurity to his Royal Highneſs. Methinks it has ſufficiently been proved, that no Body can pretend that the Letter his Royal Highneſs has writ to the King, does engage him to a down-right delivering up the Cittadel; and that if any thing has been offered, it has been done upon Terms, and ſuch as ought entirely to be to his Royal Highneſſe's liking.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:50422:16"/>
               <head>The French King's Anſwer to his Royal Highneſs the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi>'s Letter, dated <hi>May</hi> the 24th, <hi>1690.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Dear Brother,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Underſtand with great ſatisfaction, by your Letter which Monſieur <hi>Catinat</hi> has ſent me, the Reſolution you have taken to put into my Hands the Cittadel of <hi>Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rin</hi> and <hi>Verrue;</hi> and ſeeing that the Count of <hi>Provane</hi> is not here, and that if I ſhould ſtay for his arrival, to hear what he has to ſay to me from your Part, there would be waſted a conſiderable Time, in which the march of my Troops towards the Dutchy of <hi>Milan</hi> would be put off; I thought fit to ſend to the Sieur <hi>Catinat,</hi> a full Power to receive thoſe Places in my Name; and in the mean time I am willing to aſſure you, by this Letter, that I have been very much troubled to find my ſelf obliged to give Orders for my Troops entring your Territories; and that as ſoon as I ſhall have no cauſe to doubt of your Zeal for my Intereſt, and of that conſtant Affection for my Crown, of which moſt of your Anceſtors have given many ſubſtantial Proofs, I will render you my Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip with pleaſure, and do that for you which your near Relation gives you reaſon to hope for.</p>
               <p>I am, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:50422:16"/>
               <head>His Royal Highneſs's Chancellor's Letter to Monſieur <hi>Catinat, June</hi> the 3d, <hi>1690.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>HIS Royal Highneſs has been extreamly troubled to underſtand, by what I have told him of your in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincible Reſiſtance, to accept thoſe Propoſals I have made you in his Name, the Misfortune he has not to be able to ſatisfy his Majeſty, and to ſee that ſo many ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Endeavours of his to pleaſe him, have been altogether unſucceſsful. It is without doubt the Effect of my little Capacity to make them agreeable, which I am alſo heartily ſorry for. But thinking that his Royal High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs's Propoſals concerning the Places and Troops, were ſo very liberal and juſt, that they wanted no Art of Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torick, I received with pleaſure his Orders to make them known to you. I wiſh with all my Heart that you would be pleaſed to aſſiſt me with your great Experience of the Affairs of the World, to find out ſome other more ſucceſsful Expedient. I will do all that lies in my Power to make them acceptable to his Royal Highneſs, as alſo to let you ſee by my care, the Honour I have to be real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly yours, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:50422:17"/>
               <head>Monſieur <hi>Catinat</hi>'s Anſwer to the Chancellor's Letter, dated <hi>June</hi> the 3d, <hi>1690.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Have received the Letter, you have done me the honour to write to me, which I find to be writ with the ſame Spirit as all his Royal Highneſs's Miniſters have diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered to me in our Converſations. I have found no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that has been poſitive in all the Treaties I have had the honour to have about a Buſineſs of ſo great Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, except the Promiſes that have been made to the King by his Royal Highneſs, in a Letter which he has had the honour to write to him with his own Hand.</p>
               <p>I am, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Monſieur <hi>Catinat</hi>'s Letter to his Royal Highneſs, <hi>June</hi> the 16th, <hi>1690.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Monſiegneur,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Have to day received an Expreſs from his Majeſty with ſuch Orders, that may give ſome means to your Royal Highneſs to help your ſelf out of thoſe Extreams which you your ſelf have drawn upon you. For this Reaſon I beſeech your Royal Highneſs to ſend to me two or three of your Miniſters, whom you have moſt conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in, that I may make it known to them; for the going and coming of which I take the liberty to ſend you Paſs-ports. I humbly beſeech your Royal Highneſs
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:50422:17"/>to do me the honour to believe that I am, with a deep reſpect, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>His Royal Highneſs's Anſwer to Monſieur <hi>Catinat</hi>'s Letter, dated <hi>June</hi> the 17th, <hi>1690.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>YOU have as many Witneſſes as you have Soldiers, of what I have ſuffered, to ſhow my reſpect for, and readineſs to ſerve the King your Maſter. You know I did conſent to your Demand, about ſome of my Troops going into <hi>France;</hi> that you ſhow'd a great ſatisfaction about it to the Marqueſs <hi>Ferrero,</hi> as if it had been your only deſign in my regard, and that you told him we ſhould hence forth look upon the King's Troops as Friends. Nevertheleſs, ſome few days after you wanted ſome of my ſtrong Places; afterwards you deſired that, contrary to your firſt Propoſals, my Troops were not to go into <hi>France,</hi> but to join your Army in order to act againſt the Dutchy of <hi>Milan.</hi> After which you ſee that I have reaſon to wiſh, that in caſe you had ſomething to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to me, you would do it in Writing, and I will do the ſame. This is all that I can ſay at preſent in Anſwer to your Letter, and that I will always preſerve thoſe Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timents of eſteem for you, with which I am, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:50422:18"/>
               <head>Monſieur <hi>Catinat</hi>'s Reply to his Royal Highneſs's Anſwer, <hi>June</hi> the 17th, <hi>1690.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Monſiegneur,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Have received the Letter your Royal Highneſs has done me the honour to write to me, in which your In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions are ſo clear and evident to follow thoſe Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments you have embraced a great while ago, that it is needleſs to propoſe you any thing in Writing that may give ſome means to recover the Honour of his Majeſty's Favour. I am, with all that reſpect that is owing to you.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:50422:18"/>
            <head>Books Printed for <hi>Richard Baldwin.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>A True Relation of the Cruelties and Barbarities of the <hi>French,</hi> upon the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Priſoners of War. Being a Journal of their Travels from <hi>Dinan</hi> in <hi>Britany,</hi> to <hi>Thoulon</hi> in <hi>Provence,</hi> and back again. With a Deſcription of the Scituation, and Fortifications of all the Eminent Towns upon the Road, and their Diſtance. Of their Priſons and Hoſpitals, and the Number of Men that died under their Cruelty; With the Names of many of them, and the Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of their Deaths and Burials: With an Account of the great Charity and Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings of the poor Proteſtants of <hi>France;</hi> And other material Things that hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned upon the Way.</p>
            <p>The Memoirs of Monſieur <hi>Deageant;</hi> containing the moſt ſecret Tranſactions and Affairs, from the Death of <hi>Henry</hi> IV. till the beginning of the Miniſtry of the Cardinal <hi>de Richelieu.</hi> To which is added, a particular Relation of the Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Embrun</hi>'s Voyage into <hi>England,</hi> and of his Negotlation for the Advancement of the Roman Catholick Religion here; together with the Duke of <hi>Buckingham's</hi> Letters to the ſaid Arch-Biſhop, about the Progreſs of that Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fair; which hapned the laſt Years of King <hi>James</hi> I. his Reign. Faithfully tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated out of the <hi>French</hi> Original.</p>
            <p>The Cabinet Open'd; or, The Secret Hiſtory of the Amours of Madam <hi>de Maintenon</hi> with the <hi>French</hi> King. Tranſlated from the <hi>French</hi> Copy.</p>
            <p>The Hiſtory of the moſt Illuſtrious <hi>William</hi> Pr. of <hi>Orange;</hi> Deduc'd from the firſt Founders of the Ancient Houſe of <hi>Naſſau;</hi> together with the moſt conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable Actions of this preſent Prince. The ſecond Edition.</p>
            <p>A Collection of Fourteen Papers, relating to the Affairs of Church and State, in the Reign of late King <hi>James.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Character of a Trimmer. His Opinion of, I. The Laws and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. II. The Proteſtant Religion. III. The Papiſts. IV. Foreign Affairs. By the Honourable Sir <hi>William Coventry.</hi> The third Edition, carefully Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected, and cleared from the Errors of the firſt Impreſſion.</p>
            <p>An Impartial Relation of the Illegal Proceedings againſt St. <hi>Mary Magdalen</hi> Colledg in <hi>Oxon,</hi> in the Year of our Lord 1687. Containing only Matters of Fact as they occurred. The Second Edition. To which is added the moſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable Paſſages omitted in the former. Collected by a Fellow of the ſaid Colledg.</p>
            <p>The Juſtice of the Parliament, in inflicting of Puniſhments ſubſequent to Offenders vindicated; and the Lawfulneſs of the preſent Government aſſerted.</p>
            <p>An Account of Mr. <hi>Parkinſon</hi>'s Expulſion from the Univerſity of <hi>Oxford,</hi> in late Times; in vindication of him from the falſe Aſperſions caſt upon him, in a late Pamphler, Intituled, <hi>The Hiſtory of Paſſive Obedience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Way to Peace among all Proteſtants; being a Letter of Reconciliation, ſent by Bp <hi>Ridley,</hi> to Bp <hi>Hooper.</hi> By Mr. <hi>Sam. Johnſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Purgatory prov'd by Miracles; collected out of <hi>Roman-Catholick</hi> Authors. With ſome Remarkable Hiſtories relating to <hi>Brittiſh, Engliſh,</hi> and <hi>Iriſh</hi> Saints. With a Preface concerning their Miracles. By Mr. <hi>Sam. Johnſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Seaſonable Diſcourſe, ſhewing the unreaſonableneſs and Miſchiefs of Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition in Matters of Religion; Recommended to a ſerious Conſideration. By Mr. <hi>Andr. Marvel,</hi> late Member of Parliament.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:50422:19"/>
            <p>
               <hi>The Revolter.</hi> A Tragi-Comedy, acted between the <hi>Hind</hi> and <hi>Panther,</hi> and <hi>Religio Laici.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Collection of Poems, Satyrs, and Songs, againſt Popery and Tyranny. In four Parts. Moſt of them writ by the late Duke of <hi>Buckingham,</hi> Mr. <hi>Andrew Marvel,</hi> Mr. <hi>John Aylof,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Stephen Colledge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>An Anſwer to the Bp. of <hi>Rocheſter</hi>'s firſt and ſecond Letters, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Intrigues of the <hi>French</hi> King at <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> to imbroil <hi>Chriſtendom;</hi> diſcovered in ſeveral Diſpatches paſt between him and the late Grand Signior, Grand Vizier, and Count <hi>Tekeley;</hi> all of them found in that Count's Papers. With ſome Reflections upon them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Plain Engliſh.</hi> In relation to the Real and Pretended Friends to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Monarchy. Humbly offer'd to the Conſideration of his Majeſty, and his Great Council, the Lords and Commons in <hi>Parliament</hi> Aſſembled. <hi>The ſecond Edition.</hi> With a ſhort <hi>Preface,</hi> and an <hi>Appendix,</hi> concerning the Coronation Oath adminiſtred to K. <hi>James.</hi> II.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The New Nonconformiſt.</hi> Or, Dr. <hi>Shertock</hi>'s Caſe in preaching after a Depriva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, incurr'd by the expreſs words of a Statute; fairly Stated and Examined. With ſome ſhort Reflections upon Mr. <hi>Cook</hi>'s Sermon, <hi>Feb.</hi> 2. 1690. which was Licens'd by the Arch-Biſhop's Chaplain.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Fate of France.</hi> A Diſcourſe where it is ſhew'd, That by the <hi>Happy Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volution</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> all the Deſigns of the <hi>French</hi> King for the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy</hi> are diſappointed; and the rational Grounds to believe his Downfal near. In Dialogues betwixt Father <hi>Petre,</hi> Father <hi>La Chaiſe,</hi> and two <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Anatomy of a Jacobite Tory.</hi> In a Dialogue between <hi>Whig</hi> and <hi>Tory,</hi> occaſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the Act for Recognizing King <hi>William</hi> and Queen <hi>Mary.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Great Baſtard, Protector of the Little One.</hi> Done out of <hi>French.</hi> And for which the <hi>French</hi> King put forth a <hi>Proclamation,</hi> with a Reward of five thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand <hi>Louis d'Ors,</hi> to diſcover the Author.</p>
            <p>Reflection upon a Form of <hi>Prayer,</hi> lately ſet forth by the <hi>Jacobites</hi> of the Church of <hi>England;</hi> and of an Abhorrence, rendred by the late King, to ſome of our Diſſenting Biſhops, upon his preſent Majeſty's Landing.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eſſex</hi>'s Innocency and Honour vindicated; Or, <hi>Murther, Subornation, Perjury,</hi> and <hi>Oppreſſion,</hi> juſtly charg'd on the Murderers of that Noble Lord, and True Patriot, <hi>Arthur</hi> (late) Earl of <hi>Eſſex.</hi> As prov'd before the Right Honourable (late) Committee of Lords, <hi>are ready to be Depoſed.</hi> By <hi>Laurance Braddon,</hi> Gent.</p>
            <p>To the two Univerſities an Epiſtle; together with a Prediction concerning the French; tranſlated out of <hi>Callimachus,</hi> who is by Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> ſaid to be a Prophet, and that his teſtimony is true, <hi>Titus</hi> 1.12, 13.</p>
            <p>The Secret Hiſtory of the Dutcheſs of <hi>Portſmouth;</hi> giving an account of the Intrigues of the Court during her Miniſtry: and of the Death of <hi>K. C.</hi> II.</p>
            <p>An Addreſs given in to the late King <hi>James,</hi> by the Titular Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Dublin,</hi> from the general Meeting of the Romiſh Biſhops and Clergy of <hi>Ireland,</hi> held in <hi>May</hi> laſt, by that King's Order; wherein ſeveral things relating to the Popiſh Deſigns upon theſe three Kingdoms are diſcovered; the Original where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of was found in the late King <hi>James</hi>'s Cloſet in the Caſtle of <hi>Dublin</hi> at his lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving that City, and the Copy whereof was found in the Titular Arch-biſhop's Lodgings. Now publiſhed, with Reflections on each Paragraph.</p>
            <p>The Folly of Prieſt craft. A Comedy.</p>
            <p>The Royal Flight, or the Conqueſt of <hi>Ireland.</hi> A Comedy.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
